Guide to the Mariette Pathy Allen Photographs and Papers, 1968-2003 RL.00028
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mariette Pathy Allen photographs and papers
1968-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Allen, Mariette Pathy
RL.00028
8.5 Linear Feet
Documentary photographer based in New York City. Collection contains five portfolios of Allen's work, dating from the 1960s to 2003, totaling 131 color and black and white prints that document aspects of human sexuality, gender identity, the connections between people and art, and the social life of people in Philadelphia and New Jersey suburbs and beaches. The prints are arranged into these series: Transformations: Crossdressers and Those Who Love Them; The Woman Who Lives Inside: Portraits of Men as Women; NJ/PA 1968; People and Art; and the Gender Frontier. A final series consists of a group of papers and publications by and about Allen. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts.
Approximately 931 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Mariette Pathy Allen Photographs and Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase and gift from 2006-2010.
Biographical Note
Documentary photographer based in New York City.
Collection Overview
Collection contains five portfolios of Allen's work, dating from the 1960s to 2003, totaling 131 prints that document aspects of human sexuality, gender identity, the connections between people and art, and the social life of people in Philadelphia and New Jersey suburbs and beaches. The first series, Transformations: Crossdressers and Those Who Love Them contains eleven 15.5 x 23 inch color prints mounted on 24x31 inch mat board. These photographs are from the book of the same title published in 1990 that documents crossdressers in everyday life. The second series, The Woman Who Lives Inside: Portraits of Men as Women, is a portfolio of 16 gelatin silver and 15 color prints. The third is entitled NJ/PA 1968, containing 28 black and white, 16x20, gelatin silver prints. Images include people at the New Jersey beaches, east coast suburbs, and Philadelphia. A fourth series consists of 30 16x20 gelatin silver prints entitled People and Art, shot between 1968 and 2000. Photographs include artists at work, people looking at art, the Venice Bienniale 1999, Paris, London, and Budapest. Finally, the fifth series consists of 31 color and black and white prints from Allen's 2004 book, The Gender Frontier, documenting transgender and transsexual people in relationships, at conferences and political rallies, and undergoing corrective surgeries. This series also includes many portraits of different transgender people. Two CD-Rs of Allen's images are also included in the Papers Series, which also houses printed materials, brochures, and articles that include photographs by Allen. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts.
Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Social life and customs; New Jersey -- Social life and customs; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Pictorial works; Gender identity -- United States; New Jersey -- Pictorial works; Documentary Photography; Gelatin silver prints; Color photographs; Documentary photographers; Black-and-white photographs; CD-ROMs; Portrait photography; Artists -- Portraits; Transvestites -- United States -- Portraits; Transvestites -- United States -- Pictorial works; Transsexuals -- United States -- Portraits; Transsexuals -- United States -- Pictorial works; Transgender people -- United States -- Portraits; Transgender people -- United States -- Pictorial works; Transgender people -- United States; Allen, Mariette Pathy. Gender Frontier; Allen, Mariette Pathy. Transformations; Allen, Mariette Pathy; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Transformations: Crossdressers and Those Who Love Them, 1978-1989, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  A portfolio of eleven 15.5x23 inch color dye photographs from the 1990 book Transformations: Crossdressers and Those Who Love Them that documents crossdressers in everyday life.
  - Photographic prints, 11 15.5x23 inch prints (Box 1)
- The Woman Who Lives Inside: Portraits of Men as Women, 2 boxes
  A portfolio of 16 gelatin silver and 15 color prints.
  - Photographic prints and two matted exhibit panels with introduction and captions, 16 silver prints (Box 2)
  - Photographic prints with one matted panel with captions, 15 color prints (Box 3)
- NJ/PA 1968, 1968, 2 boxes
  Twenty-eight black and white, 16x20, gelatin silver prints. Images include people at the New Jersey beaches, East Coast suburbs, and Philadelphia. A CD-ROM with images from this series is available in the Papers Series.
  - Photographic prints, with thumbnails printed on paper (Box 4-5)
- People and Art, 1968-2000, 2 boxes
  Thirty 16x20 gelatin silver prints of artists at work, people looking at art, the Venice Bienniale 1999, Paris, London, and Budapest. A CD-ROM with images from this series is available in the Papers Series.
  - Photographic prints (Box 6-7)
- The Gender Frontier, 1992-2003, 2 boxes
  Twenty-one 16x20 gelatin silver prints and ten 16x20 digital color prints on Fujifilm Crystal Archive Paper and Fuji Color Paper from the Allen's book, The Gender Frontier, published in 2004. The images document the lives of transgender and transsexual people throughout the United States. Subjects include relationships, families, and political and cultural events such as the True Spirit Conference, Transgender Lobby Day, and the Gay Pride parade in New York City. Includes several color photographs documenting the corrective surgeries and transition of Tanya to Tony, including his chest reduction and phalloplasty. Photographs in this series are marked with Allen's captions and signature.
  - Photographic prints, black-and-white (Box 9)
  - Photographic prints, color (Box 10)
- Papers Series, 1968-2003, 3 boxes
  Documentation of Allen's career including printed materials, brochures, articles, and clippings. Publications include photographs and writings by and about Allen and her career. There are also two CDs with digital images of Allen's portfolios entitled NJ/PA 1968 and People and Art.
  - Papers and CD-ROMs (Box 8)
  - Papers (Box 11)
  - Papers (Box 12)